<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd to the Societies for Reformation of Manners in the citys of London and Westminster. February, 19. 1699. Published at their request. By Thomas Reynolds.</title>
            <author>Reynolds, Thomas, 1667?-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1322A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222106</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833336</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833336</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57195)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2196:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd to the Societies for Reformation of Manners in the citys of London and Westminster. February, 19. 1699. Published at their request. By Thomas Reynolds.</title>
                  <author>Reynolds, Thomas, 1667?-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Richard Mount on Tower Hill, and John Lawrence in the Poultrey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37812:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd to the SOCIETIES FOR <hi>Reformation of</hi> MANNERS, In the CITYS of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>February,</hi> 19. 1699.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed at their Requeſt.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS REYNOLDS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Mount</hi> on <hi>Tower Hill,</hi> and <hi>John Lawrence</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37812:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37812:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful <hi>Sir</hi> THOMAS ABNEY, AND <hi>Sir</hi> OWEN BUCKINGHAM Knights, and Aldermen of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Eſteem it a favourable Providence, that my firſt appearing thus publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould be in defence of ſo Noble a Cauſe, as that of Reforming the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Wicked Men, which has over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb facs="tcp:37812:3"/>the reluctance I had to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of this Diſcourſe. And the Poſt you bear in the Government of this Renowned City, beſides the honour of being admitted to your Acquaintance, hath emboldned me to offer it to your Patronage.</p>
            <p>The ſuppreſſing of Vice and Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which have too long been the Reproach of our Nation, is ſuch a work, as requires the Aſſiſtance of all that have any regard to Religion or Virtue: and it is not the leaſt of our Publick Bleſſings, that ſo many of your Rank and Quality are ready to lend their helping hand to it.</p>
            <p>This is a Deſign that greatly becomes Perſons in your Station, and is truly worthy of Thoſe that bear the higheſt Character. Your Zeal therefore in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting it will be your Glory while liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a conſiderable comfort to you in the hour of Death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37812:3"/>
            <p>They who act in a lower Sphere direct their eyes to you for encouragement; and they are ſuch as You that muſt ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate 'em, and make 'em chearful in their work, who otherwiſe will be apt to faint and be diſcourag'd.</p>
            <p>You are better known than to need the diſplay of Your worthy Characters. And I much rather chuſe to be ſilent than incur the leaſt imputation of Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery. Yet I hope you'l pardon me that I have declared You the Friends of Virtue, and the Promoters of what is aimed at in the following Sermon, by Dedicating it to You.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you to accept it as a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my unfeigned Gratitude for the Favours I have received from you: And eſpouſe what I have end eavour'd to recommend to Perſons of all Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that You may be reckon'd among our valuable Bleſſings; and as you
<pb facs="tcp:37812:4"/>outſhine others in the Honours of this World, you may partake of a larger ſhare in the Glories of the other: which is the Humble and Hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged, and moſt Obedient Servant, Thomas Reynolds.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37812:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. ix. 7, 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He that reproveth a Scorner, getteth to himſelf Shame: And he that rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a wicked Man, getteth himſelf a Blot. Reprove not a Scorner, leſt he hate thee—</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HOW improper ſoever theſe words at their Firſt view may ſeem to the preſent occaſion of our Meeting, a little Patience and Attention it's hop'd will beget in you other conceptions about them.</p>
            <p>I have not choſen them to become an Advocate for Vice, or to lay Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their way, who are vigorouſly bent to ſuppreſs it. No, my Brethren, it is ſo far from my purpoſe to abate your Zeal, that I would do my uttermoſt to increaſe and inflame it. And I heartily pray, that wicked men may be ſooner weary of their ſins, than you in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37812:5"/>them in all thoſe ways, and by all thoſe Methods that are becoming, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and lawful.</p>
            <p>And altho my Text may carry a face contrary to what I pretend; yet I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe my ſelf ſome conſiderable advantage in drawing an Argument from it, that I preſume will be allow'd to have ſtrength in it, both for the juſtifying your Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Proceedings, and encouraging your Perſeverance therein.</p>
            <p>It is more than probable ſome may from hence raiſe an Objection againſt you; and for this very reaſon it is neceſſary theſe words ſhould be conſidered and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, both for your own ſatisfaction, and the confuting of thoſe who would be glad to lay hold on any thing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to diſparage and give a check to that good Work you are engaged in.</p>
            <p>If I ſhew that theſe words are not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againſt your aſſiſting the Civil Magiſtrate in puniſhing Profane and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Men, but from what they are really oppos'd unto, they render it your indiſpenſible Duty; may I not hope hereby to wreſt out of the hands of your Enemies one of the principal Weapns
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37812:5"/>they may uſe againſt you, and ſo do ſome Service to your Cauſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that reproveth a Scorner, getteth to himſelf Shame: and he that rebuketh a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man, getteth himſelf a Blot. Reprove not a Scorner, leſt he hate thee</hi>—</p>
            <p>And is this all that's to be gotten (may the Objector ſay) by reproving Scorners and wicked men? Is this all the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to be expected? What wiſe man then would engage in ſo fruitleſs a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and beſtow his Pains where he is like to meet with ſo bad a Requital? Were it not better to ſit ſtill at home and ſleep in a whole Skin, than by <hi>caſting Pearls before Swine,</hi> or endeavouring to pull them out of the Mire, to provoke them to turn and rend us? What man will parley with an Enemy, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of bringing him to terms of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance he is ſure before-hand to be torn and cut to pieces by him? Who would venture to reprove wicked men, when they inſtead of being ſoftned and reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thereby, will but be the more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd, and wound our Innocency while we are ſtriking at their Vices? Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prudence and Self-preſervation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37812:6"/>would teach us to forbear in ſuch a Caſe. But the rather ſhould we do it when Wiſdom her ſelf favours us with her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and expreſly forbids us to <hi>Reprove a Scorner leſt he hate us,</hi> implying that he certainly will do ſo, and this is all we are like to get from him whatever kind Intentions we bear towards him.</p>
            <p>Now it is of dangerous conſequence to draw upon our ſelves the hatred of wicked men; Men who have no Fear of God before their eyes, who are profeſſed Enemies to all that is Good, who have baniſh'd their Reaſon and debauch'd their Conſcience, who matter not what they ſay or do, nor which way their Tongues or their Hands are employ'd ſo they can but diſcharge their Malice upon us.</p>
            <p>And this being ſo as Wiſdom her ſelf who cannot err aſſures us, Attempts for reforming the Manners of Scorners and Wicked men would ſeem a vain and hazardous undertaking: A Work that a Wiſe man would be ſhy of, and no man is under any Obligation to engage in, nay under an expreſs Charge to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37812:6"/>
            <p>If therefore by medling in a Matter which doth not belong to them, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to themſelves no other Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their Pains, than Shame and a Blot, that is, all the Dirt and Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that wicked Men can rake together and throw upon them; they muſt charge it to their own Imprudence, and thank themſelves, for if they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Wiſdom's Advice, they would not have done it.</p>
            <p>This Objection hath not (as I know of) been deſignedly taken notice of by any of my Brethren that have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, yet deſerves to be conſidered as that which not only may be urged by profeſſed Enemies to your worthy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, but by thoſe who pretend to be of the wiſer, that is, the more wary and cautious ſort of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And indeed this is an Objection they may be very fond of, becauſe it ſeems to carry ſome Plauſibleneſs with it, and chiefly becauſe it is an Arrow taken out of your own Quiver; for thus they will pretend to direct your own Weapons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and ſtab your Cauſe with that very Sword you uſe in defence of it.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37812:7"/>But this, like an Arrow beſides the Mark, does no execution; or rather, like one directed into the Sky, falls down again, and wounds his Head who ſhot it.</p>
            <p>To make this clear and evident, I have propos'd to my ſelf this Method in diſcourſing upon the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to give you the true genuin Senſe and Meaning of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Anſwer a Query that will na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally reſult from hence: And this in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third</hi> and laſt place will yield me a very fair Opportunity to expoſe the Weakneſs and Impertinency of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; and to make it evident, that what Advantage may be had from theſe words, in the caſe under conſideration, lies on your ſide, and againſt your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Firſt</hi> for the Senſe of the words, there are three things which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our Enquiry: as,</p>
            <p>Who is deſign'd by the <hi>Scorner</hi> and <hi>Wicked Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the <hi>Reproof</hi> we are forbidden to miniſter nto ſuch?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37812:7"/>
            <p>How are we to underſtand the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition when it is ſaid, <hi>Reprove not a Scorner leſt he hate thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Who is deſign'd by the <hi>Scorner</hi> and <hi>Wicked Man?</hi> I reply, one and the ſame Perſon is underſtood. For it is agreed on all hands that it's the manner of the Wiſe Man to repeat the ſame thing in the ſame verſe in other words throout all this Book. A Scorner is one of the worſt of Men: He is a confirmed and hardned Sinner, one who refuſes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and is ſo incapable of <hi>Reproof, that nothing will move him to become bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> And therefore Wiſdom paſſes ſuch by, and leaves them to their wretched Folly as Perſons to be deſpaired of; while thoſe who being <hi>merely inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and deluded,</hi> ſhe invites to her Houſe, becauſe ſuch (it were to be hoped) might become willing to receive her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2. of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>Again, the Scorner is one who if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd will but requite you with <hi>Shame</hi> and a <hi>Blot,</hi> that is, will not only make you loſe your labour, and thereby give occaſion to others to deride the Vanity
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37812:8"/>of your Attempt, but like an ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Wretch will deride and ſcoff at you himſelf, as tho it were not enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject your good Offices, but he muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe you into the bargain.</p>
            <p>He is one, who will malign and hate you, and whilſt you reprove him, will but throw Dirt in your face, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward traduce you behind your back; till he hath made you as black by Slanders and Reports as his Crimes have rendred him <hi>in Reality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And are there not many ſuch Scorners in our times? Monſters! ſhall I ſay of Men? yea Monſters of Sinners too! moſt Impious Wretches! who being perfectly hardned in Wickedneſs, will hearken to nothing that might tend to reform or better them. They are too big to be ſpoken to, too proud to be inſtructed, too ungrateful to take any thing kindly at your hands. To endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to reform them, is but to give them an occaſion to become worſe, ſince Contumelies and Curſes, Scorn and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, a Hiſs and a Scoff is the Reward you muſt expect. Theſe are thoſe whom we may well ſuppoſe pointed at by St.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37812:8"/>
               <hi>Jude,</hi> concerning whom he ſpeaks, that <hi>there ſhall come in the laſt days Mockers walking after their ungodly Luſts, Senſual, not having the Spirit.</hi> ver. 18, 19.</p>
            <p n="2">II. What is the Reproof here forbidden?</p>
            <p>Reproof is <hi>Verbal</hi> or <hi>Real.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verbal</hi> is the more Gentle way of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Sinners, by ſpeaking to them, and reaſoning the Caſe ſoberly with them, conveying our Reproofs as whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Phyſick in the Vehicle of ſoft words and friendly admonitions. An Inſtance of this we have in the firſt Chapter of this Book of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> where Wiſdom is repreſented as uttering her words, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>How long ye ſimple ones will ye love Simplicity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Turn you at my reproof: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I will pour out my Spirit unto you, I will make known my words unto you.</hi> v. 21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Real</hi> Reproof is a rougher way of handling them, and is the laſt Remedy that is left, which therefore is not to be uſed till other Methods are found fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and ineffectual upon them. This is perform'd by corporal Puniſhments and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37812:9"/>penal Mulcts: And to this thoſe words may refer which you have in the 19th Chapter of this Book; <hi>Judgments are prepared for Scorners, and Stripes for the back of Fools,</hi> ver. 29. And there we are directed to <hi>ſmite a Scorner, and the Simple will beware,</hi> v. 25. that is, to puniſh a Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Religion ſeverely, which tho it do Him no good, may reclaim Others, or at leaſt make them more cautious and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>Now to which ſort of Reproofs the Words of my Text do refer, will be very eaſily determin'd, by any one that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiders what goes before and follows after. For I muſt by the way obſerve, that altho in the Chapters which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, there is ſeldom any Coherence either of the Senſe or Sentences, but they lie as ſo many precious Pearls looſe and unſtrung; yet here, and in what hath been hitherto delivered of this Book, there is a very plain Connexion, and the Senſe like the precious Ore in a rich Mine, runs along in one continued Vein, as an ingenious Author makes the Compariſon.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37812:9"/>
            <p>To any one therefore who conſiders the Reſpect the words of the Text have to what precedes and follows, it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear beyond all doubt that the Reproofs which are here forbidden muſt be confin'd to thoſe which are managed in a way of Counſel and Advice, Admonition and Entreaty, and all thoſe other Methods of Argument and Perſuaſion, whereby <hi>Ordinarily</hi> the Miniſters of the Word or private Perſons would endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim Wicked men from their ſins: And that here is nothing in the Text or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text that hath the leaſt ſhadow of a reference to that ſort of Reproof which conſiſts in the puniſhing Offenders by the Sword of the Civil Magiſtrate. For in the beginning of this Chap. Wiſdom is repreſented as a glorious Princeſs dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in her Stately Palace, and ſending forth her Agents to invite poor ſimple Souls to her Houſe to hear the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of her Mouth, which will yield as much Pleaſure and Satisfaction to the minds of her Scholars, as the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Banquet or delicious Feaſt to their bodily Appetite. And further, the Text ſtands in a manifeſt Oppoſition to <hi>ver.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37812:10"/>19th, where it is ſaid, <hi>Give Inſtruction to a wiſe Man and he will be yet wiſer, teach a juſt Man and he will increaſe in Learning.</hi> So that upon the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text it appears that the words refer only to the Verbal reproving of Scorners.</p>
            <p n="3">III. And laſtly, How are we to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Prohibition when it is ſaid, <hi>Reprove not a Scorner leſt he hate thee?</hi> This may be taken, either <hi>Abſolutely</hi> or <hi>Comparatively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolutely,</hi> And ſo we are to let him alone; and as to what reſpects this way of dealing with him, to leave him wholly to himſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſuppoſes ſome former Trials, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by our ſelves or others, and that there is the fulleſt Proof of his Obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Incorrigibleneſs. Which being ſo, we are not to ſpend any further Time and Pains to no purpoſe upon him, but paſs him by as a deſperate Wretch, with whom other kind of Methods muſt be taken.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37812:10"/>
            <p n="2">2. It may be taken in a Comparative Senſe, which is frequently to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> where the Negative Adverb is commonly put for the Particle of Compariſon, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.10. <hi>Receive my Inſtruction and not Silver,</hi> i. e. ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Silver. It immediatly follows, <hi>and Knowledg rather than Choice Gold.</hi> So Joel 2.5, 13. <hi>Rend your Hearts and not your Garments,</hi> i. e. rather rend your Hearts than your Garments. And ſo may we not accommodate this Hebraiſm to the words of the Text? <hi>Reprove not a Scorner leſt he hate thee, but</hi> (as is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſubjoin'd) <hi>rebuke a Wiſe Man and he will love thee;</hi> that is, Reprove not a Scorner, but rather beſtow your Reproofs upon thoſe who will receive Good by them, and heartily thank you for them. We ſhould much ſooner turn to a wiſe Man, one that will hear Reaſon, and think upon what we ſay, than one where all our Counſels will be rejected. Not but that ſuch Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Circumſtances may happen wherein it may be our Duty to reprove the worſt of Scorners to teſtify our Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of the Sin, even when we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37812:11"/>not better the Man. But uſually and for the moſt part we ſhould apply our ſelves to thoſe who will hear us, where there is the greateſt likely hood of doing Good, with the leaſt Damage at the ſame time to our ſelves. And ſo the words teach us to make a wiſe and diſcreet Choice of the Perſons we would admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and not heedleſly to expoſe our ſelves to the Contempt and Obloquy of ſcornful men: But when all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances conſidered there is the greateſt Reaſon to believe that we ſhall neither do Good to the Perſon we reprove, nor to Others, nor bring any Glory to God, but only draw down an Inconvenience upon our ſelves, in ſuch a Caſe we are to forbear our Reproofs.</p>
            <p>And thus it moſt commonly happens with reference to the openly Profane and Wicked. Such generally do but make a mock of Sin, and deride every thing that carries the face of Seriouſneſs with it. To tell ſuch of their Sins, does but exaſperate them the more; to check them in their Career, is to make them fly out with the greater Violence; and to offer to controul them, is to inflame
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37812:11"/>their Wrath, and increaſe their Hatred againſt us.</p>
            <p>Here then it is fitting we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and hold our Hands, becauſe when we can do no Good we ought not to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter an Occaſion of further Evil; and ſince we cannot ſuppreſs Mens Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, we ſhould not do any thing that might provoke it: Herein acting conſonantly to thoſe words of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Lord, who thought fit to adviſe us <hi>not to give that which is Holy unto Dogs, nor to caſt our Pearls before Swine, leſt they trample them under their Feet, and turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and rend us,</hi> Matth. 7.6.</p>
            <p>But yet, as I have already obſerv'd, this is not ſo abſolute a Rule, but may upon ſome extraordinary Emergency admit of an Exception: And it may ſo fall out that we ſhall find our ſelves under an Obligation to ſpeak up boldly for the Glory of God, tho we deſpair at the ſame time of any Good to the Sinner. Yea By-ſtanders by conſidering our Place, Profeſſion and Character, may expect ſomething from us: And to avoid being accus'd of Connivance or Cowardice, we may find our ſelves bound to take
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37812:12"/>ſome notice of Scorners: tho to ſpeak properly, I think this is not ſo much a reproving of them, as a clearing of our ſelves.</p>
            <p>When this is to be done, and How, and what are thoſe Circumſtances that muſt determine us, as I have not time, ſo neither do I judg it fit for me to aſſign. This muſt be left to a Man's own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Prudence; and it being a very nice and critical Point, he hath the more Reaſon to look up to God for his Aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Direction: But ſetting aſide ſome rare and ſpecial Emergences, the Inſtruction the words afford us is to be the Rule of our Conduct towards Scor ners and Wicked Men. And this leads me to a Query which doth Naturally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult from hence, which is the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second</hi> thing propos'd, in anſwering of which I ſhall not only remove the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection that hath been ſtarted, but make it undeniably appear, that becauſe we are forbidden to reprove a Scorner in the plain Senſe of our words, for that very Reaſon we are indiſpenſibly bound to reprove him in the Senſe that our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries oppoſe.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37812:12"/>
            <p>The Query then is this, If we are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden to reprove Scorners and wicked Men in a way of Counſel, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Admonition, and the like; pray what muſt be done, or what other courſe muſt be taken with them? In anſwering of this Inquiry, I ſhall undertake to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That they muſt not abſolutely be let alone, that is, be left to purſue their helliſh Courſes with that full Swinge and Liberty, as to be entirely without all manner of Controul. But,</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the ſupreme Governour of all things, in his great Wiſdom and Mercy to the World, hath appointed other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of dealing with ſuch irreprova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sinners.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That they muſt not abſolutely be let alone ſo to purſue their helliſh Courſes, as to be without all manner of Controul. The Reaſons of this are ſo ſtrong and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, and the Abſurdities of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuppoſition ſo groſs and palpable, that there are none who do not wilfully
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37812:13"/>ſhut their Eyes, but muſt readily aſſen to the truth of it. And as for Scorners themſelves, if we could as eaſily turn their Wills, as convince their Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of this, we ſhould not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently put to ſilence all their Objections, but ſave them from thoſe Severities which otherwiſe they muſt ſhortly fall under, and it may be before they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeak ſomewhat to this, there needs no more to prove it than to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the contrary: Suppoſe that Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were to be wholly uncontroul'd, to live as they pleaſe, and do what they liſt. The Conſequences of this will appear to be ſuch, as muſt render it abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Honour of God, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Religion, the maintaining com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Order, and the Peace and Welfare of Humane Societies, that ſome Courſe be taken at leaſt to reſtrain and curb them.</p>
            <p>For if no notice were to be taken of them; if men of prophane and atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Principles, of unbridled Luſts and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, haters of all that is Good, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen deriders of God and Godlineſs, were to be let alone to follow the depraved
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37812:13"/>Byaſs of their wicked Hearts, to what a paſs muſt the World be reduc'd in a little time?</p>
            <p>The Vices of Men would not only grow up to an Exceſs of Boldneſs and Inſolence, but the Infection would ſpread like a raging Peſtilence, or like a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Fire, which tho at firſt it break out but in one Houſe, and might have been eaſily quench'd, yet being let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone proceeds farther till it hath turn'd the whole City into a ruinous Heap.</p>
            <p>Sinners would hearten one another up and take Courage, others would be more eaſily induc'd to fall in with them. Their Zeal for Licentiouſneſs (O that we were as zealous againſt it!) would make them indefatigable in uſing all imaginable Methods to ſtrengthen their Party, and increaſe the Number of their Proſelytes. And if <hi>now,</hi> after all the Endeavours the Reforming Societies have us'd to diſcourage them, they ſwarm in ſuch Numbers among us, how would they then overſpread the Face of the whole Earth, and like a general De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge drown all Mankind firſt in Sin, and then in Perdition?</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37812:14"/>
            <p>If Men might be ſuffer'd not only to revile Religion, but openly to renounce Calling upon God, to prophane his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, to Curſe and Swear, to Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme his Holy Name, to commit all the Outrages againſt Heaven they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, and to be guilty of all manner of Immoralities: What would become of Religion, the Worſhip of God, and all that Honour we owe to him, and ſhould be ſo tender of?</p>
            <p>If Men might purſue their inordinate and beaſtly Luſts without Interruption, who would be ſafe either in the Street or in their Houſes? And as we might ſuppoſe the Number of the Good at ſuch a time to be very ſmall; ſo how would they be as ſo many <hi>Lots</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Sodom,</hi> who had it not been for a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Interpoſition of God, could not have kept himſelf from the violence of thoſe filthy Wretches, tho in his own Houſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.11.</p>
            <p>In a word, If wicked Men were to paſs on wholly uncontroul'd, there would be in a little time no Temperance, no Sobriety, no Chaſtity, no Truth, no Faith, no Juſtice, no common Honeſty:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37812:14"/>But Beaſtlineſs and Senſuality, Leudneſs and Debauchery, Injuſtice and all kind of Immorality would take place of Religion, and baniſh all Virtue out of the World. The bands of all humane Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety would be broken; and as Men would daily grow worſe and worſe, ſo they would not only bring ruin upon others, but ſudden deſtruction upon themſelves: not only as ſuch extravagant Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would haſten down the Judgments of God, as it did upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah;</hi> but as there would need no more utterly to deſtroy them than their own inordinate Luſts and outragious Paſſions.</p>
            <p>And theſe being now the moſt certain, natural and neceſſary Conſequences of mens unreſtrained Vices and Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (as none will deny) it does then moſt unqueſtionably follow, that they muſt not be thus let alone, but that ſome courſe or other muſt be taken to repel and rebuke, to conquer or at leaſt to curb and put a ſtop to their prevailing wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without which Religion and the honour of God would ſoon fall to the ground, and all the bands of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Order and Government be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37812:15"/>broken and torn to pieces. So that the World could not long ſubſiſt if Vice were wholly without a check, but would of neceſſity ſoon periſh by its own wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſupreme Governour of all hings, in his great Wiſdom and Mercy to the World, to prevent its ſpeedy and haſty ruin, hath appointed other ways and methods of dealing with ſcornful and incorrigible Sinners, who will not be reclaimed by mild and gentle Reproofs. He hath appointed that which ſhall have more force upon them, than the ſtrongeſt Reaſons in the world. They ſhall be conſtrain'd to do that which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perſuaded to; they ſhall be forc'd and driven to it even againſt their wills. When fair Words and Intreaties, ſober Admonitions, and friendly Advice will not prevail upon them, but they perſiſt to ſin openly in the face of the Sun, to the ſcandal of Religion, the contempt of the Laws, and the diſhonour of God; they are to find, that tho God may have ſeal'd up our Mouths, he hath not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ty'd up our Hands: And we muſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37812:15"/>make them do that by outward force and compulſion, which they will not do by entreaty and perſuaſion. The ſtripes and corrections of the Rod, and other mulcts and puniſhments, muſt ſupply the defects of the Word: And the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate muſt compel them to that, which Miniſters and other good People can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by ſofter Methods obtain from them.</p>
            <p>Therefore for this end God hath inveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Civil Magiſtrate with power to reſtrain and puniſh ſuch daring Offenders. He is ſaid to be <hi>the Miniſter of God, a Revenger to execute wrath upon him that doeth evil,</hi> Rom. 13.4. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place is ſaid <hi>to be ſent of God for a Puniſhment of evil doers,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.14. He hath his Authority from hence (as tho he were ſent down from thence to take cognizance of inſolent Rebels) and it is God who ſmites, tho by the hands of men.</p>
            <p>And as it is the indiſpenſible Duty of the Magiſtrate to employ his power for God, in puniſhing the bold Impieties of theſe men: As he is not <hi>to bear the Sword in vain,</hi> but to uſe it in ſuppreſſing their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37812:16"/>Vices and reforming their Manners, as well as for other ends and purpoſes; ſo it is no leſs the Duty of every one in his private Station and Capacity to be aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Magiſtrate in ſubſerviency hereunto; by diſcovering Offenders, and bringing them to Juſtice, by taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of thoſe who break the Laws, and proceeding againſt them in order to legal Conviction, that ſo they may be juſtly puniſhed; ſuch as Blaſphemers, Sabbath-breakers, Drunkards, Whoremongers, and the like prophane and beaſtly Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; ſuch as deride and ſcoff at Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who make a mock of Sin, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in their ſhame, who hate the Reproofs of the Mouth, and deſpiſe all manner of Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Scorners in my Text, and for theſe the Laws are made; theſe are the proper Objects of puniſhment; Stripes are prepared for the backs of ſuch Fools as theſe. The Sword is put into the hand of the Magiſtrate on purpoſe to be exerciſed upon theſe men, becauſe by no other means or methods is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hope of bringing them to terms. And therefore tho we are forbidden to reprove
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37812:16"/>ſuch, yet we are not abſolutely to let them alone, or to ſuffer them to go uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul'd in their wickedneſs; but to apply ourſelves to thoſe other Methods of dealing with them, which God hath appointed, that ſo hereby they may be brought to ſome amendment: and if they cannot be reform'd in their Principles, they may in their Manners; and altho there were no hope of bettering them, there might be ſomewhat done to prevent their hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of others: as rude and ſavage Beaſts, which (tho you cannot change their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) may be chained up from doing further Miſchief.</p>
            <p>And our aſſiſting the Magiſtrate to this end, is what we are all of us in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Stations and Capacities obliged to both as Men and as Chriſtians. To this we are indiſpenſibly bound, as we tender the Honour and Glory of God, the good of the Society of which we are parts, the Welfare of our Families, the Authority of the Magiſtrate; as we would not partake of other Mens ſins, nor be guilty of their Blood; and as we would put a ſtop to the ſpreading of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and avert the heavy judgments of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37812:17"/>God, or procure thoſe farther deſirable Bleſſings we may need. And this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, then in the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third</hi> and laſt place, how fair an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity doth this give me, and what Scope does it afford to expoſe the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and impertinency of the Objection, which your Adverſaries might pretend to raiſe from theſe words to diſcourage your noble Undertakings? How evident doth it now appear, that your Oppoſers are ſo far from gaining an advantage againſt you from hence, that on the contrary who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhould offer to urge theſe words, would not only be preſently put to ſhame and ſilence, but have the weapon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he thought to ſtab your Cauſe ſheath'd in his own Bowels? I mean, his own Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument would be turned into one of the ſtrongeſt Arguments againſt him.</p>
            <p>How little pretence have any to argue from theſe words againſt your aſſiſting the Civil Magiſtrate in puniſhing of leud and notorious Sinners? It is true, we are not to uſe verbal Reproofs to a Scorner, we are not ordinarily to ſpend our Breath upon ſo vile and impious a wretch, we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37812:17"/>are not to admoniſh and counſel him; but are to forbear uſing any further Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and Perſuaſions with him. And what then? muſt the Magiſtrate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not have any concern with him? or we not yield our aſſiſtance to the Magiſtrate? whence do they infer this? where is the <hi>Nexus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how convincing and clear is the reaſoning on the other ſide? Becauſe we are not to miniſter verbal Reproof to the Scorner, and yet his wickedneſſes are ſuch as upon no account to be tolerated; therefore and for that very reaſon we are to join with the Civil Magiſtrate in doing our utmoſt to ſuppreſs their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations: for which very end the Sword is delivered from God into his hands, that ſo they who will not be brought into order by methods of Reaſon, may be compel'd and forc'd into it by mulcts and bodily puniſhments. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning here is cloſe and pertinent, ſo clear and natural, and ſo ſtrictly ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and united, that all the malice of wicked men, and the ſubtilty of all the Devils in Hell will never be able to break the force of it.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37812:18"/>
            <p>But yet after all we have ſaid, I am ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive our Adverſaries may reſume the Objection, and proceed to reply: We will acknowledg it is probable, they may ſay, that the Text may be wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to the verbal reproving of Scorners, and ſo far it muſt be granted that our Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is not pertinent or valid. But notwithſtanding, the reaſon on which the Prohibition in the Text is founded, is applicable to your caſe, and if it holds true and hath force in the one, why may it not in the other?</p>
            <p>Now is it not plain that in the method you take of reproving Scorners and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men by the power of the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, you incur their hatred and malice? In your way of dealing with Sinners don't you make good the words, in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to your ſelves <hi>Shame and a Blot?</hi> doth not your own daily Experience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and verify it? do not the many Sermons that have been preach'd and printed acknowledg it? a good part of which is taken up in ſolacing you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Calumnies and Reproaches of Scorners. And if here, in the ſenſe given of the Text, you are not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37812:18"/>a Scorner leſt he hate you, and not to rebuke him leſt you get to your ſelves Shame and a Blot, why ſhould you not then for the ſame reaſon be forbidden to reprove him by the Civil Magiſtrate?</p>
            <p>I ſhall give as ſhort an Anſwer to this as I can, tho many things might be ſaid unto it.</p>
            <p>It is falſly ſuggeſted that we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to reprove a Scorner merely or ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the account of ſhame and hatred. For I have ſhewn you, that when by verbal reproving a Scorner there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to be got but ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, no good end or purpoſe can be ſerv'd that might ballance the preſent evil we ſuſtain by adminiſtring our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs: that is, there is no good to be done to the Perſon we reprove, nor to others, neither any Glory to be brought to God; there is nothing redounds from our pains but a reproach to our ſelves, and a further exaſperating of the wicked wretch: In ſuch a caſe, we are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and forbear our reproofs. But if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe great and noble Ends I have mentioned might be obtained; if by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing our ſelves to ſhame we might
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37812:19"/>bring glory to God, or do any good, theſe are ſuch valuable ends, that we ſhould not only be willing to ſacrifice our Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but all we had for the ſake of them.</p>
            <p>And this now is the caſe with reference to our aſſiſting of the Civil Magiſtrate, which makes it vaſtly different from that in my Text. For by bringing Offenders to puniſhment, tho we incur the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches and malice of wicked men, yet we do thereby anſwer ſuch good ends and purpoſes as do infinitely out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh the particular loſs or evil we may ſuſtain in the faithful diſcharge of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For to inſtance hereby,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. Sometime a great deal of good is done to the perſon we reprove, he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed and reformed, or prevented from growing worſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. A great deal of good is done to others, they are warned and admoniſhed thereby.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. A great deal of evil is prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that might reſult from mens uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled Impieties. And,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, a great deal of glory is brought to God, as Religion is defended, God's Honour is maintained, his Name is reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37812:19"/>the Authority of the Magiſtrate is upheld, and Order and Government is kept up in the world: <hi>Each one</hi> of which ends, if but one might be attained, is <hi>ſo valuable,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> put together ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakably advantageous, and ſuch a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral good, that no man ought, nay no good man (that duly conſiders it) can be unwilling to ſacrifice his Name and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, nay to venture his Life for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of them.</p>
            <p>And if in our Endeavours hereunto we get to <hi>our ſelves</hi> ſhame and a reproach, we might uſe the Scripture expreſſion, and ſay, if this is to be <hi>vile, we will yet be more vile,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.12. Let them call me Informer, Buſy-body, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worſe names, I'll matter them not. Let them heap up all the Dirt they can upon me, I will ſtill purſue theſe great ends. Much more might be ſaid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſilencing of this part of the Objection; but this I judg to be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
            <p>Having thus conſider'd and opened the Text, clear'd the Senſe, and removed the Difficulties which might ſeem to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, and brought them to ſerve you
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37812:20"/>Purpoſes inſtead of making againſt them, I now proceed to the Applicatory part of my Diſcourſe. And,</p>
            <p n="1">I. By way of <hi>Inſtruction</hi> in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Reflections: as here we may take notice,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the precipitancy and imprudent raſhneſs of ſome well meaning People, who will plentifully beſtow their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations and good Counſels where they might reaſonably expect not only to be rudely treated themſelves, but that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion alſo ſhould ſuffer upon their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. They fall to the reproving of Sin wherever they meet it, without any conſideration had of the Perſon that commits it; and ſo for want of obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rule of my Text, have done diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to Religion, and gain'd no credit to themſelves. <hi>It is good to be zealouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in a good thing</hi> (as ſome of you have heard in a worthy Diſcourſe from thoſe words of the Apoſtle) but then our Zeal ſhould be temper'd with Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is, I muſt confeſs, a moſt rare and commendable Virtue, yet thro an impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent miſplacing of it may iſſue in very
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37812:20"/>bad effects. But the Inſtances of thoſe whoſe zeal doth tranſport them beyond their knowledg in this particular are <hi>ſo few;</hi> and of ſuch whoſe zeal doth not keep pace with it, <hi>ſo many,</hi> that I think it not needful to enlarge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may obſerve the adorable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, in preſcribing this rule for our conduct toward Scorners and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men. Such is his regard to our peace and quiet, to our good Name and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that he would not have us em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our pains where we may not reap the pleaſant Fruits of our labour, nor expoſe our reputation where there is not a proſpect of bringing more Glory to him by our reproofs, than ſhame to our ſelves. Which one conſideration ſhould methinks be an irreſiſtible motive to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us cheerfully to comply with the Duty of reproving, ſince we are only oblig'd to it, when the accruing Benefit and Reward will unſpeakably counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail all the Trouble, Hazard, and Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty which may attend the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The words do alſo lead us to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the moſt deplorable condition of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37812:21"/>Scorners and Wicked men; how uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivably ſad their caſe muſt be, in being thus left of God, and all good men, in being deprived, nay in depriving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of one of the greateſt Bleſſings un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven. For what a Bleſſing is it to have a faithful Friend, who will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh us of our faults, that ſo Iniquity may not prove our ruin?</p>
            <p>To be deprived of this is to be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of one of the greateſt mercies, and of a moſt ſutable and likely means of our Salvation: yet this you ſee is the ſad caſe of thoſe who deride Religion. For not only <hi>Solomon,</hi> but a greater than <hi>Solomon,</hi> our Saviour Chriſt himſelf, hath forbidden us to miſplace reproofs upon thoſe who are deſperate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The whole Tenour and Strain of what hath been delivered, doth not only evince the neceſſity of Civil Magiſtracy and Government, in order to lay a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon the Corruptions, and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Manners of thoſe men in whom no Counſels or verbal Reproofs will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the deſired effect: But ſhews us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, how great and publick a mercy it is to enjoy ſuch Magiſtrates as will righteouſly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37812:21"/>execute the Laws upon theſe Offenders, and who, if there be any that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict them, will take care that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch puniſhments as their crimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. Such Magiſtrates are publick bleſſings indeed, and as they are <hi>ſent of God,</hi> are the Inſtances of his good will to Mankind.</p>
            <p>Vice runs every thing into diſorder and confuſion: whatever therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains and keeps this from breaking forth, ought to be acknowledged as a great bleſſing, as it is a binding up mens hands, to prevent their deſtroying themſelves, and hurting others.</p>
            <p>And this again makes it evident that Magiſtracy is from God, that it is not from the evil Spirit, who as he at firſt loſt his own happineſs, by ſtepping out of his proper place and rank, would by introducing the ſame diſorder ruin the World, and deſtroy Mankind by the ſame methods whereby he undid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>The powers that be, are ordain'd of God,</hi> Rom. 13.1. And the Magiſtrate, as I have before obſerv'd, is <hi>ſent of God;</hi> that is, tho not the Man, yet the Office and the Power comes down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37812:22"/>and this in infinite mercy to a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful World, which hath not ſo much as a Principle left for its common preſervation, but if abandon'd to its own Inclinations would hurry into ruin.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And this farther informs us of the honour of the Civil Magiſtrate, and what regards we are to bear to him, even no leſs than to God's Vice-gerent, and the Guardian of our Laws: which ſhould ſtrike us with aw, and direct us to carry it towards him with the higheſt Reſpect and Reverence. Such are ſaid to be the <hi>Gods of the Earth,</hi> Gods in Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as they ſhould be alſo in other Godlike Excellencies. How high a Poſt, how honourable a Station then are they ſet in! But which certainly is then moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, when they are moſt ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and do moſt throughly purſue and anſwer the ends of their appointment. And this again.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Inſtructs thoſe in their duty who have any concern or influence in the choice either of ſuch perſons as are to concur in enacting Laws for us, or of ſuch whoſe place it is to ſee them execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It is moſt plain from all that hath
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37812:22"/>been hitherto ſaid, that we are not to be directed merely by a great Eſtate, or by regard to a Party, or biaſs'd by Relation, Affection, Dependance, private Intereſt, and ſuch like mean ſelfiſh and mercenary Motives: But we are to take our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures from the nature and ends of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and therefore laying aſide all particular and by reſpects, and having nothing but the glory of God and the good of the Community in our eye, we ſhould make choice of ſuch Magiſtrates as will diligently take care and ſee that the good Laws we have be duly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially executed, men (as the Holy Scripture deſcribes them) <hi>fearing God and hating Covetouſneſs,</hi> who are no Reſpecters of Perſons; who will not be warp'd by bribery, fear, or private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards; Men of real Integrity and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity, men of Fidelity, Juſtice, Courage and Boldneſs; who will not fear the face of Man in the cauſe of God; who when Offenders are convicted, will be ſure to puniſh them. Where ſuch are to be found is not my place to direct, but yours to enquire.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:37812:23"/>
            <p>And then again, having choſen ſuch Magiſtrates, it is our duty to obey them, and in our ſeveral ſtations and capacities to yield them all the aſſiſtance we can, and not to render them, ſo far as in us lies, only great Cyphers in their Office thro the want of our help; but that Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity being found out, it may be brought under the correction of Juſtice. As you can do nothing without the Authority of the Magiſtrate, ſo neither will he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do much without your help and aſſiſtance. You are to be as Eyes to him in bringing criminal matters under his cognizance, and he to be as Hands to you in correcting and puniſhing them.</p>
            <p>Now as a motive to urge and enforce all this upon you, I would deſire you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider that the obtaining of ſuch choice bleſſings, as good Repreſentatives, faithful Magiſtrates, and ſubſervient Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, lies much in your own power. For you (my Brethren) enjoy this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Privilege above many Nations, <hi>viz.</hi> the right (in many caſes) of chooſing theſe perſons.</p>
            <p>If at any time therefore it ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den (which God forbid) that there
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37812:23"/>ſhould be any effectual Laws wanting for the ſupreſſing of Vice and Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; or, ſuppoſing good Laws, there ſhould not be a ſufficient Magiſtracy of thoſe (who come under your choice) to put them in execution; or if on the contrary, Iniquity ſhould be eſtabliſhed by a Law, or publickly connived at, much of all this would be owing to your ſelves, for that by your care and diligence at firſt you might (in a great degree how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) have prevented it. The miſeries which muſt enſue from ſuch a poſture of affairs might be look'd upon as a juſt puniſhment of your negligence, and it would then be in vain to cry out or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the ſlackneſs of the Laws and badneſs of the times; for why did you not uſe the means that were once in your own power to guard againſt theſe evils? Thus much by way of Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. To proceed:</p>
            <p n="2">II. What I have endeavour'd to prove in the foregoing Diſcourſe, does afford abundant matter for the <hi>juſtifying</hi> your noble and generous undertaking of ſuppreſſing the Vices and reforming the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37812:24"/>Manners of Wicked men. This is your duty, and the ſenſe of duty ſhould bear you up under the greateſt cenſures and reproaches. Beſides whatever you may incur of this nature, yet by doing your duty you will anſwer (as I have ſhewn you) ſuch great ends and purpoſes, as will make amends for all your trouble and hazard in the performance of it. Let men go on to condemn you, you may be ſure God will juſtify you; and is it not unſpeakably better to be cenſured of men for doing your duty, than to be condemned of God for the neglect of it?</p>
            <p>But why ſhould any condemn you? If a man's houſe were infected with the Plague, will any body blame you for ſhutting up his Doors? If thoſe very Perſons who exclaim ſo much againſt you ſhould have their Houſes on fire, would they reproach and revile you for endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to quench the Flames? And if a worſe Peſtilence and Fire be broken out, if men grow rampant in Wickedneſs, and run up and down ſpreading the contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as tho Hell were broke looſe, muſt you be blam'd for endeavouring to put a ſtop to it?</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:37812:24"/>
            <p>Will Men thank you for lending a helping hand to ſave them from tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral evils and dangers? and ſhall they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach you for labouring to deliver them from eternal ruin? It will put a man to great pain to have his Leg or Arm cut off, yet he will not blame the Chirurgion, when it is to ſave his life; and muſt you be blam'd for puniſhing a Sinner to ſave his Soul? O ungrateful creatures, that will thus requite your kindneſs to them!</p>
            <p>But let us conſider a little; If you are to be blam'd, it is either becauſe,</p>
            <p>The Matter you are engaged in is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Or it does not concern you.</p>
            <p>Or the Methods you take in the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it are unjuſtifiable.</p>
            <p>As for the Matter and Work it ſelf, my whole Diſcourſe hath been a full and clear Juſtification of it.</p>
            <p>To ſay it do's not concern you, is very abſurd and fooliſh. What! does it not concern you to vindicate the honour of God? to bring Glory to his Name, the thing you were made for? Does it not concern you to avert the Wrath and Judgments of God from the Land, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37812:25"/>to preſerve your ſelves, your Families, and the Nation from ruin? What doth concern you if this doth not?</p>
            <p>To ſay your Methods are unjuſtifiable, this is what I preſume they can never prove after they have made thoſe allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, which in a matter of ſuch publick nature and extent all mankind muſt own to be reaſonable and juſt.</p>
            <p>As for your entring into Combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Societies: They cannot reproach you for this, when they conſider the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Regularity of them. This hath been already ſufficiently juſtified by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand; and (as that Reverend Perſon expreſſes it) 'tis no other thing than what is conſtantly done without offence in caſes of <hi>Secular</hi> concernment. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, can Wicked men think it no offence to combine and club together, to carry on the deſigns of Hell in debauching and damning one another? And ſhall not we aſſociate and combine together to prevent their ruin, if it be poſſible?</p>
            <p>As for the Rules and Orders that are obſerved among you; do not very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judges highly approve them? and if any condemn them, are they not for the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37812:25"/>moſt part ſuch as betray a very apparent malice or ignorance?</p>
            <p>The only thing that ſeems to carry an ill face with it, yet will be found high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commendable, <hi>is the buſineſs of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, as it was manag'd in the late times, it was one of the moſt odious and diſgraceful things in the world, when a parcel of ſorry, idle and profligate Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, the ſcum of the Earth, to get a piece of Money to ſupply their neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or to ſpend upon their Luſts, would inform againſt thoſe who were forc'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Corners, and there met together not to plot againſt the Government, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to worſhip God according to their Conſciences. This was ſuch an employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that none but a generation of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers would be engaged in. And indeed there is nothing in my opinion can ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a man more infamous and odious than to be ſuch a kind of Informer. But to inform againſt the Vices and evil Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Wicked men; to inform a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Curſing and Swearing, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and Sabbath-breaking, Rioting and Drunkenneſs, Chambering and Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37812:26"/>and other ſuch helliſh and brutal Practices, what reproach can there be in this? This is what the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and beſt of men have not diſdained or refuſed, as you have had divers inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces given you by others out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>But I only ask, Is the Law or the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it to be reproach'd? why then ſhould Informing in order to execution? To have a Law that ſhall never be executed, is all one as to have no Law. And how ſhall the Law be executed if there be none to inform, and to convict Offenders in order to the bringing them to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? And where lies the diſhonour of doing our duty in this particular? This is ſo far from being a diſgrace to any man, that I muſt ſay, it is the moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of your whole work, as it diſcovers a brave and noble Spirit, that is not afraid to appear for God againſt the worſt of men. Thoſe who are moſt forward in this work, are moſt to be commended; as thoſe we reckon the beſt Soldiers, who will ſtand in the Front of the Battle, and engage in the hotteſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37812:26"/>
            <p>But to conclude, as it is every one's du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſee the Laws executed, ſo it may in divers circumſtances be every mans du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to inform. And he is to be accounted little better than a Coward, who will not engage in this piece of Chriſtian Service when fairly call'd to it.</p>
            <p>What I have ſaid therefore under this Head may be ſufficient to vindicate your Proceedings. And if there be any who will ſtill continue to rail and calumniate, it is to be ſuſpected they generally are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad men and of no reputation. And then you need value their reproaches no more than the fleerings of Fools and Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, or the loud clamour and bawling of mad Men. But having ſhewn how much there is to juſtify you of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties for Reformation of Manners, I paſs in the</p>
            <p n="3">III. Place to a Uſe of Reproof to thoſe who moſt juſtly deſerve it. And.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As for thoſe who are open Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Reformation, and are the Perſons you are to deal with, I ſhall not ſpeak to them; they are the Scorners in my Text, and therefore to be ſuppos'd very ſeldom
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37812:27"/>preſent at theſe places, and upon theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions: And if I ſhould addreſs my ſelf to them, it would be to no purpoſe, and I have too little time to ſpend my Breath in vain. Therefore leaving them wholly to your Management, I paſs them by to ſpeak</p>
            <p n="2">2. To another ſort of Perſons, of whom there is more hope, and they are thoſe who pretend to Religion as well as you, and are men of ſome Principles and Sobriety, who notwithſtanding have been too ready to condemn and caſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon you.</p>
            <p>That Prophane and Wicked men ſhould oppoſe a Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, is not to be wondred at; the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are plain and obvious, none can be ignorant of them: but that any who pretend to Religion or Sobriety, who are not openly vicious themſelves, that they ſhould diſcourage your good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, and concur to raiſe Objections againſt them, this is what ought to be deeply lamented by us. Their Reaſons muſt lye more ſecret and remote, yet I preſume it not difficult to gueſs at them. For what can they ſpring from but a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37812:27"/>narrow, contracted and ſelfiſh Principle, from the want of a generous and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Spirit, and that noble Zeal and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage wherewith you appear to be inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the cauſe of God?</p>
            <p>This indeed they blame in you as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent raſhneſs and forwardneſs, a med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with matters beyond your Sphere, and a needleſs diſturbing of your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. But to ſpeak plainly, I fear (without breach of Charity) that this is a ſubtile Artifice only to ſalve their own Reputation by wounding of yours. And therefore they are ſo liberal in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing their Cenſures upon you, that they might eſcape thoſe which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe muſt fall heavy upon their own Heads: As it uſually happens that they who are firſt in the complaint are moſt in the fault.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe alſo I think worthy to be condemned, who tho they will <hi>ſpeak</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt you, will <hi>act</hi> nothing for you. The work of Reformation may ſink or ſwim for them, they mind and matter it not, and are not at all concerned about it. Now theſe perſons are to be reprov'd for the neglect of their duty upon a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble account.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37812:28"/>
            <p n="1">1. For not aſſiſting in their own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. In ſuch a Cauſe as this, wherein the common Intereſt of Religion, and the good of our Country is ſo much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Every one ſhould appear and ſhew himſelf as there is fit occaſion. In caſe of an open Invaſion every one is ready to take Arms, and make head againſt the common Enemy, to defend their Eſtates and Liberties. And ſhall the more valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able concerns of Religion and our Souls, which are of infinitely greater Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, be invaded; and ſhall any man, can any man be ſo miſerably ſtupid and ſluggiſh, ſo very cowardly and timorous, as either to ſit ſtill and do nothing, or keep out of ſight and run away from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict?</p>
            <p>Yet this I fear is the caſe of many, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of thoſe who when an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity offers for their being ſingularly uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in an Office, ſlip away and decline it, whereby a worſe man comes in, or at leaſt hire another to ſupply it; who indeed will ſtand in the place, but take little care to diſcharge the duties of the office; they will carry the Staff, but earn their Mony as eaſily as they can.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37812:28"/>There is little to be expected from a great many who only ſerve in an Office for gain. Such will not ordinarily put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to much pains, or expoſe themſelves to notable hazards and difficulties. And may it not be fear'd that the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive that induc'd to accept of the Office, may as eaſily corrupt them in it, ſo that they ſhall have no ſtrength to hold a great Offender when a piece of Money is dropt into their hands? What I have ſuggeſted under this Head is one princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal reaſon why a Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners is not more vigorouſly proſecuted, and which I have heard very much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of; and therefore beſeech you to conſider it, and not let ſo good a Cauſe fall to the ground for want of putting your ſhoulder to the burden. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such are to be reprov'd not only for their unwillingneſs to aſſiſt in Perſon, but alſo for their backwardneſs in contributing to the Charge. And this indeed is an offence of a higher nature, becauſe it is ſo reaſonable, and at the ſame time ſo very eaſie, that methinks they ſhould not in modeſty refuſe it. This puts them to no trouble, and beſides
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37812:29"/>might be manag'd with that ſecrecy if they thought fit, that there would be no need to fear incurring the diſpleaſure of any man thereby. If they had a Cauſe of their own to be pleaded, they would not ſtarve it for want of feeing the Counſel. But if the Cauſe of God is to be pleaded, tho they are rich and abound, they will not ſpare a Farthing; and yet their Aſſiſtance in this particular is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly needed, and is a further Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Courſe of Juſtice. There are few ſuch generous Lawyers to be found who will plead in order to the conviction of a wretched Sinner, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Fee; and indeed it is their live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood, and therefore they may juſtly expect to be rewarded for it. And this is another matter I would recommend to conſideration, and beſeech thoſe that will not aſſiſt to this good work in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to contribute however towards the charge.</p>
            <p>Indeed I muſt ſpeak it to the praiſe of the People of <hi>London,</hi> that they have upon all occaſions appear'd very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to afford a bountiful aſſiſtance to the preaching of the Goſpel which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37812:29"/>to make men good. I wiſh they would be as free and generous in further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what is deſigned for the reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and puniſhing of the bad: I hope they will. But with reference to thoſe who will yield no Help or Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in either of theſe reſpects, neither in their Perſons nor with their Money; how great ſupineneſs doth it argue in them! and the ſlender regard they have to the glory of God, or the good of their Country! And how juſt might it be for God ſeverely to animadvert upon them. And ſince they would do nothing for the ſtopping the Plague of wickedneſs among us, their Families ſhould be firſt in the Infection, their Sin puniſh'd in the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and degeneracy of their Children; and when Judgments ſhall come upon the Land, they ſhould feel the firſt and ſmarteſt ſtroaks of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe are to be cenſur'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, who being in places of Power and Authority, are unfaithful in their Office, not only as they connive at Vice in not puniſhing it, but encourage it by their own Example, and browbeat and diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37812:30"/>ſuch as inform againſt Offenders that they might be brought to Juſtice. How ſad is the caſe, when they that ſhould be a <hi>Terror to Evildoers</hi> ſhall become the patrons of Vice; who inſtead of diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging Prophaneneſs and Immorality ſhall lead men on to it, and rather than uſe the Sword for the puniſhing of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſhall reach forth a ſhield to defend them.</p>
            <p>It is a Crime which we condemn and abhor, when one in a private ſtation is found unfaithful to his Truſt, tho it is in a thing comparatively trivial; how much more in the Poſt of a Magiſtrate, and in a matter wherein the good of the Publick is concern'd, where his Fidelity is too engag'd, not only in point of Honour, but under the ſacred Tie of an Oath, the breach of which does render him both perfidious and perjur'd?</p>
            <p>An evil Magiſtracy has been reckon'd of ſuch fatal conſequence to the Publick in antient Governments, that they took all imaginable care whom they choſe into ſuch a Poſt; and if any prov'd unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, they thought no Puniſhment ſevere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37812:30"/>for them. We may read of thoſe who have been flead, and the Seats of Juſtice cover'd with their skins, as a Mark of perpetual Infamy, and for a Terror to them who ſhould ſucceed in their places.</p>
            <p>And tho we have no ſuch frightful uſages among us, yet the belief of a God, and that Magiſtracy is his Ordinance, that perſons in places of Power do act under him as his Deputies and Delegates, and that they muſt give a ſtrict account another day of their truſt, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men; when the guilt of all thoſe Abominations which it was their duty to have reſtrain'd and puniſh'd ſhall be laid at their door: All theſe things, I ſay, put together, would furniſh them with ſuch conſiderations as are enough, one would think, to awaken the moſt ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and ſtupid; and make a man either afraid to take upon him the Office of a Magiſtrate, or to reſolve to execute it with the greateſt Faithfulneſs and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. I paſs to the</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And laſt uſe of Exhortation, wherewith I ſhall conclude. And,</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:37812:31"/>
            <p n="1">1. As to what more eſpecially reſpects your ſelves, who are of the Societies for Reformation; my Exhortation to you is, that watching ſtrictly over your own Lives (which ſhould be very exact and exemplary) you would continue to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and <hi>provoke one another to this good Work.</hi> Be not balk'd by any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, diſcouragements, or oppoſitions you meet with, but conſider your great Lord and Maſter, <hi>who bore ſuch contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sinners, leſt you grow weary and faint in your minds.</hi> Preſerve the ſweet Harmony and Affection that hath hitherto obtain'd among you, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the good Opinion you have of each other, ſo that the Devil and his Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries by all the ſtratagems they ſhall uſe may not be able to divide and weaken you. Go on to convince the World, that whatever particular Sentiments you may have about leſſer doubtful matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, yet in the moſt ſubſtantial, plain and neceſſary things you heartily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and can as heartily concur to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote them; appearing herein for the cauſe of Religion as the antient <hi>Romans</hi> for their Commonwealth, with whom
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37812:31"/>it was a generous principle to ſacrifice their private piques and quarrels to the publick good. And did we all employ our Zeal more this way, it would be found one of the moſt effectual means to put an end to thoſe Heats and Animoſities that have been ſo much lamented by ſober Men of all Parties.</p>
            <p>I ſhall offer but one thing more, and it is, that you would yield all the aſſiſtance to each other you can, by your often meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together to conſult and adviſe about the moſt proper methods to proſecute what you have undertaken. And might it not be of ſome further uſe in promoting this great deſign of Reformation, if (as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand there are divers Societies, ſome conſiſting of Perſons of inferior, and others of a higher Rank) thoſe of the latter ſort would favour the other more frequently with their preſence, which will very much animate and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them? like Soldiers who are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd never to fight ſo couragiouſly, as when their general Officers appear at the head of them. But this I propoſe with ſubmiſſion.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37812:32"/>
            <p n="2">2. As to thoſe you would reform: It is not needful that I exhort you to what others have ſo largely inſiſted upon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and which I believe you are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to obſerve. It may ſuffice that I only hint to you, that you would make the Word of God your guide in this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant affair: And therefore bearing no Wrath, Malice, Revenge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt any man in your hearts, but ſtrictly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Rules of Charity and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, you would ſee that with meekneſs and compaſſion, and yet with great impartiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and prudence, you endeavour to reclaim wicked Men from their Sins. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. By Verbal Reproof, if by this there is any likelyhood of prevailing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; not proceeding to rougher methods when milder ones may do, nor haſtily paſſing thoſe by as incorrigible Sinners who may not be ſo: but having found upon ſufficient trial, or being well aſſur'd upon other grounds, there is no good to be done this way; then</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. Apply your ſelves to that which God in caſes of extremity hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If they are really Scorners, deal with them as ſuch: and to ſtir you up to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37812:32"/>the vigorous proſecution of the Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe hardned and obſtinate Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, I ſhall offer a few things to your conſideration: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. That tho the foregoing Diſcourſe ſhould not fully convince you of your duty herein, yet your own enlightned Conſciences cannot but prompt you to it, and tell you that God expects it from you. Here you do not run before you are ſent, nor anſwer before you are call'd. May thoſe words therefore be always freſh in your Memory, <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thine Heart, thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer ſin upon him,</hi> Levit. 19.17. Implying that not to rebuke him is to hate him, to be acceſſary to his Damnation, and guilty of his Blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. It is your honour and glory to be engag'd in this Work: what Service is more honourable than the being employ'd in beating down the Devil's Kingdom, in lifting up the Name of God, in promoting the Peace, Welfare and Happineſs of your Country, and in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt beneficial kindneſs to your Neighbour?</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37812:33"/>
            <p>Indeed hereby we incur the anger and reproach of thoſe we have to deal with, but this is little to be regarded by us. And if we are calumniated for doing of good, we ought not to be diſcourag'd thereby, but eſteem it our honour that God hath thought us <hi>worthy to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is to be like our bleſſed Lord, who was grievouſly reviled and mocked, even by thoſe very Sinners he came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and ſave. Yet he went on in his merciful deſign, tho at laſt it coſt him his Life, and the warm Blood of his Heart. This is to be like the holy Apoſtles and Martyrs, <hi>who had trial of cruel Mockings and Scourgings, yea moreover of Bonds and Impriſonments:</hi> Yet they perſiſted in their endeavours to amend the World. And indeed who ſhould be aſham'd to be engaged in ſuch a Cauſe as this, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to die for it, ſince it is worth loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mortal Life, if it be to ſave but one immortal Soul?</p>
            <p>It may afford great comfort to us, to think that all our preſent ſhame will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to our future glory, that every reproach and calumny we ſuffer will
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37812:33"/>but add to the luſtre and brightneſs of our Crown. <hi>For theſe light afflictions,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>which are but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhall work out for us a far more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eternal weight of Glory.</hi> Who then ſhould fly back from ſuch a work? fly back! nay who ſhould not ſtrive and be ambitious to appear in it? and herein be as forward to ſuppreſs mens ſins, as they are greedy in committing 'em?</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. Conſider the advantageous op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity God hath put into your hands for the furthering your deſigns: we have a good KING, the brighteſt Ornament we have ever ſeen in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, who as he hath ſtudied, and ventured his Life to procure our <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quiet,</hi> ſo he hath not been wanting in his care that under his Government we may <hi>live in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> How often hath he expreſs'd his deſires of a Reformation? and by his Speeches to both Houſes of Parliament, and iſſuing out his Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, hath done his part to endeavour it? And ſhall the KING <hi>cry for Juſtice,</hi> and will not the People too? Would the King have us reform'd, and ſhall we hate to be reform'd?</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37812:34"/>
            <p>Again, you have many of the <hi>NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BILITY</hi> and <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGES</hi> of the Land, who in their Letter prefixt to a Book intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>An Account of the Societies for Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Manners,</hi> and worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended, <q>have publickly applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Deſign, and the Methods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd for the accompliſhing of it; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their moſt humble and hearty Prayer, <hi>That Pious men of all Ranks and Qualities, may be excited by this good Book to contribute their beſt endeavors to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a national Reformation of Manners.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, our <hi>REPRESENTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVES in Parliament</hi> have taken care there ſhould not be wanting good Laws to diſcourage Prophaneneſs and Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and have made it their humble Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to the King that he would iſſue out his Proclamation commanding all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Judges, Juſtices of the Peace, and other Magiſtrates, to put in ſpeedy execution thoſe good Laws that are now in force againſt thoſe Vices, which was accordingly done.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, you have many good <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> that hold up the Sword ready to ſmite, and only want your bringing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37812:34"/>Offenders to Juſtice. You eſpecially of this <hi>City</hi> are honour'd with this Bleſſing. The CHIEF MAGISTRATE, like an Illuſtrious Head, communicates Life and Vigour to the Body Politick. On theſe occaſions he countenances <hi>you</hi> (my Brethren of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) with his preſence in your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and all of us with his Power; and may he with the reſt of his Brethren continue to do ſo. May he carry the Sword triumphantly through this City, driving Sinners before him, who are timorous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough when Juſtice looks them in the face. May he entail a laſting honour upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by thus honouring of God; and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, may he thus ſet a truly great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to thoſe that ſhall ſucceed him.</p>
            <p>And now being favoured with ſo fair a juncture and opportunity, having all this to countenance you, a good King, good Laws, good Magiſtrates, and good men of all Ranks and Qualities to own you, how ſhould this inſpire you with Zeal, and embolden you in your Work? And how much of guilt will lie at their door who act in a private capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, if a Reformation of Manners be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37812:35"/>not vigorouſly carried on! Stir up your ſelves therefore, and be of <hi>good Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and the Lord of Hoſts will be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4ly. And laſtly, conſider the ſucceſs you have hitherto had, and let that encourage you. You have met with many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but have ſurmounted them. You have begun the work, and that was the greateſt difficulty of all; don't faint therefore, but go on. Some have been reform'd by you, and bleſs God heartily for it, and more have been reſtrain'd. I hear your Societies increaſe, and are ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; may they do ſo ſtill. This will put Sinners out of heart. They begin to give ground; do you not only maintain yours, but purſue them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>thus,</hi> if out of a conviction of your duty, and an aim at the glory of God, joining a pity to Sinners with your puniſhing of 'em, and praying God to bleſs thoſe Puniſhments to them, you vigorouſly proſecute your charitable and noble Undertaking, you will do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of good, you will at leaſt drive Sin into corners; and tho men ſhould not ceaſe to commit it, you will
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37812:35"/>no longer behold it; and if you cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move guilt from their Perſons, you will from the Nation. You will avert the heavy Judgments of God, and draw down a Bleſſing upon your ſelves, your Families, the Land; and when you have done your work, and your life is ended, Men will have reaſon to ſay as they are following you to your grave, we accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the Corps of one, <hi>who while he liv'd was a Reformer of this World, and is now gon to live in a better.</hi> But how ſhort is this of that Commendation which your departed Spirits ſhall have, when intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd into the preſence of your glorified Maſter, whoſe Intereſt you have induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promoted, and who thereupon will openly acknowledg and abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it by ſaying, <hi>Well done good and faithful Servant, enter into the Joy of your Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
